<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ccnet | ZeroSharp]]></title>
  <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/blog/categories/ccnet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-21T09:47:49+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://ZeroSharp.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CruiseControl Notifications on your iPhone]]></title>
    <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/cruisecontrol-notifications-on-your-iphone/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T11:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ZeroSharp.github.com/cruisecontrol-notifications-on-your-iphone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/blog/ccwatcher-002.jpg" width="200"></p>

<p><a href="http://sixafter.com/portfolio/continuous-integration-monitoring-for-ios/">CCWatcher</a> is a great iPhone app for any developer who is using CruiseControl.NET, Jenkins or Hudson for their continuous integration.</p>

<p>We have used <a href="http://www.cruisecontrolnet.org/">CruiseControl.NET</a> for several years to automate all builds. The build kicks off automatically whenever we push changes and this frequently happens a few times a day. We aim to have everything <em>green</em> at the end of every day.</p>

<p>A full build with unit tests and functional tests takes about an hour, so often, I will leave the office while the build is still running. But then I wouldn't know if I'd broken the build.</p>

<p>For a long while I was looking for a better way of being informed of build failures on my phone.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/blog/ccwatcher-001.png" width="300"></p>

<p>Enter <strong>CCWatcher</strong>. It's a simple application which allows you to enter the address of your build server and it will tell you the status of the projects you've configured.</p>

<p>Whenever I need to check whether I've broken the build, I can just <em>pull to refresh</em>.</p>

<p>When I first discovered the application it had a problem with CruiseControl.NET's <a href="http://cruisecontrolnet.org/projects/ccnet/wiki/RemoteServices">remote services</a> (which we needed because the actual build server is on a network machine not visible from the internet). I contacted <em>SixAfter</em> and was very impressed with the helpful response from Michael Primeaux. Within a couple of weeks there was a new version of the app with support for the remote services configuration. Hats off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
