<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: space | ZeroSharp]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/blog/categories/space/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-23T17:30:09+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The only robot on any other planet]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/the-only-robot-on-any-other-planet/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-30T08:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/the-only-robot-on-any-other-planet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is part of an ongoing series about robots, past and present.  See <a href="/musical-interlude/">Musical Interlude</a>.</p>

<h3>The Mars <em>Opportunity</em> Rover</h3>

<p><em>Opportunity</em> landed on Mars in January 2004.  It is currently the only active robot on any planet other than Earth (until the scheduled arrival of <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P4boyXQuUIw"><em>Curiosity</em></a> in August 2012).  The mission was originally supposed to last 90 days.</p>

<p>The rover contains pieces of the fallen World Trade Center which were turned into shields to protect cabling.</p>

<p>This photo of the Endeavour Crater on Mars was taken by the <em>Opportunity</em> rover on March 9, 2012.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/the-only-other-robot-001.jpg"></p>

<h4>Hardware - if it ain't broke, don't fix it</h4>

<p>NASA prefers hardware that has been used successfully on previous missions, even if it means compromising on performance.</p>

<p>The computer on board is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_RAD6000">RAD6000</a>. It is single board computer designed for the US Air Force by BAE Systems with a 32-bit processor based on the IBM RISC single chip CPU.  It has 128 MB of RAM.It is radiation hardened so that it can withstand the harsh environment of space. The RAD6000 is reported to cost between USD 200,000 and USD 300,000.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's a venerable board. We've used it ever since the Mars Pathfinder Mission what — about 12 years ago, 14 years ago?</p><footer><strong>Peter Gluck,</strong> <cite><a href='http://news.oreilly.com/2008/07/the-software-behind-the-mars-p.html'>The Software Behind the Mars Phoenix</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<h4>Lifecycle</h4>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Opportunity_-_Cratera_Eagle.jpg"><img class="right" src="/images/blog/the-only-other-robot-002.jpg" title="Eagle Crater landing site" ></a></p>

<p>The software on a Mars lander is expected take 3-4 years development.
It's designed according to a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model">Waterfall</a> model split roughly as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>9 months requirements definition</li>
<li>12-18 months in design phase</li>
<li>12-18 months test phase</li>
<li>Launch!</li>
</ul>


<h4>Software</h4>

<p><blockquote><p>One of the things about the software, one of the unique aspects about working software on a spacecraft is it's the only part of the system that you can change after launch.</p><footer><strong>left</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The operating system is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VxWorks">VxWorks</a>.  The software on board the spacecraft is entirely in <em>C</em>.  The software on the rover is about 650,000 lines of <em>C</em>.</p>

<pre><code>#include void main() { printf("Hello Mars\n"); }
</code></pre>

<p>No GitHub.  Most space technology software is considered arms technology, so it cannot be made open source.</p>

<h4>References</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.universetoday.com/95358/opportunity-gets-a-view-from-the-edge/">Universe Today blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://news.oreilly.com/2008/07/the-software-behind-the-mars-p.html">The Software Behind the Mars Phoenix</a> Audio interview with Peter Gluck</li>
<li>Image credits NASA/JPL-Caltech</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Skiing on Mars]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/skiing-on-mars/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-27T11:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/skiing-on-mars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Mars_propm_rover.jpg"><img class="right" src="/images/blog/skiing-on-mars-003.jpg"></a>
This post is part of an ongoing series about robots, past and present.  See <a href="/friends-robots-countrymen/">Friends, Robots, Countrymen</a>.</p>

<h3>The Soviet PrOP-M Rovers</h3>

<p>In May 1971, the USSR launched two rovers to explore Mars.  <strong>They were to move on skis (!!)</strong> while connected to the landers with 15m umbilical cables.</p>

<p>The first one crash landed.  The second landed sucessfully but failed twenty seconds after landing and never moved.  The reasons are unknown although the landing took place in the middle of a dust storm.  The base module did manage to transmit about 20 seconds worth of the <strong>first ever photograph of the surface of Mars</strong>, shown on the left here.  According to the Soviet Academy of Sciences there is nothing, horizon or otherwise, identifiable in this photograph.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Mars_3_Image.png"><img class="left" src="/images/blog/skiing-on-mars-001.png"></a>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Soviet_Union-1972-Stamp-0.06._Mars_2.jpg"><img class="right" src="/images/blog/skiing-on-mars-002.jpg"></a></p>

<p>The rover itself, although never deployed, was equipped with sensors to detect obstacles (the two foremost metal bars in the photograph above).  <strong>The rovers were somewhat autonomous</strong> and capable of navigating obstacles.  The Soviet engineers were aware they might not have enough time for a remote-controlled operation of the rover (one-way communication takes between 4 and 20 minutes to Mars).</p>

<p>Receiving a signal from another planet, even for a few seconds is such an incredible achievement.  It's difficult to imagine what it was like being a programmer in those days, under that regime, but it must have been dramatic for those involved.  Hope, fear, pride, joy and perhaps disappointment and regret. <strong>All because of a chunk of metal sitting in a red dust storm <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=distance+between+mars+and+earth+on+December+2+1971">141 million kilometres</a> away.</strong></p>

<h3>Analog Computers</h3>

<p><a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/145669/what-software-programming-languages-were-used-by-the-soviet-unions-space-progra">Apparently</a> any programming would have been done on analog computers.  An analog computer does not require 'software' in the sense we use the term today.  Instead the computer evaluates an <em>analog</em>, a 'model' which corresponds to a given problem. You create the model by describing differential﻿ equations which correspond to the problem and then deriving a circuit corresponding to these equations. This is the 'program' of the analog computer. The computer itself has no memory and no algorithmic program control.</p>

<p>Watch a demonstration of how to program an analog computer to simulate a mass-spring system.  <strong>It's a far cry from my day job.</strong></p>

<p><iframe width="640" height="390" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/H_4bFgYReq0 " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>

<h4>References</h4>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_2">Wikipedia Mars 2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_3">Wikipedia Mars 3</a></li>
<li><a href="http://cyberneticzoo.com/?p=3830">Cybernetic Zoo</a></li>
<li><a href="http://weburbanist.com/2011/12/04/star-cars-10-past-present-future-robot-space-rovers/">Star Cars: 10 Past, Present &amp; Future Robot Space Rovers</a></li>
<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/space/interview/interview-przhiyalkovsky.htm">Interview with Viktor Przhiyalkovsky</a></li>
<li>Images via Wikipedia</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
