<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: macbook | ZeroSharp]]></title>
  <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/blog/categories/macbook/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-23T17:12:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ZeroSharp.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Macbook and the mysterious sleep]]></title>
    <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/macbook-and-the-mysterious-sleep/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-23T16:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ZeroSharp.github.com/macbook-and-the-mysterious-sleep</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally worked out why my Macbook was randomly sleeping.</p>

<p><strong>TL;DR</strong> - <a href="#anchor-tldr">Skip to the end</a>.</p>

<h2>Clues</h2>

<p>It only seemed to happen when I was working while sitting up on the bed with the computer on my lap. It seemed to be related to the position of the computer or possibly the lid. The computer would sleep. I'd wake it and login again. Continue. Sometimes it would happen once. Sometimes three times in ten minutes. Annoying. I assumed some hardware defect.</p>

<h2>Pajamas</h2>

<p>Then over several days I cracked it. I realised it never happened when I was wearing pajamas. Very strange.</p>

<h2>Reflections</h2>

<p>I started thinking about what normally triggers sleep mode. Closing the lid. How does a Macbook know the lid is closed. There's not really a clasp or anything so it must be a magnet. Perhaps it's getting confused by my belt buckle or something. My phone?</p>

<p>No, my phone <em>case</em>! The flip-case of my phone has a magnet to keep the flap closed. In my jeans pocket it's near enough to make the laptop think the lid has been closed. Duh.</p>

<h2><a name="anchor-tldr"></a>TL;DR</h2>

<p>Take your mobile phone out of your pocket!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The best PC laptop is a Mac]]></title>
    <link href="http://ZeroSharp.github.com/the-best-pc-laptop-is-a-mac/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-09T17:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ZeroSharp.github.com/the-best-pc-laptop-is-a-mac</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>A month ago</h3>

<p>I've never liked laptops. The screen seems so small. A powerful laptop is too heavy; a light one doesn't cut the mustard.
I can't even find the on/off switch.</p>

<p>Then there are those fancy new <strong>Macbook Pro</strong>s with retina displays. They seem light and powerful and the screen looks great. I don't know much about Macs, but I'd like to learn.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>But I need Microsoft Windows and Visual Studio. I know theoretically I can run a virtual machine or setup a dual boot, but I'll bet it's all a bit of a hassle and rather clunky...</p></blockquote></p>

<h3>Three hours after my Macbook Pro arrived</h3>

<p>Windows 8 is installed and looks absolutely beautiful! The font is small, but the screen is so sharp that it is quite readable. Visual Studio looks great with the font size in the editor Window set to 14 or 15.</p>

<p>The installation was much simpler than most other Windows installations I've done. I followed <a href="http://www.iclarified.com/entry/index.php?enid=20961">this tutorial on iClarified</a> to set up a dual boot. You use a tool called the Bootcamp Advisor which is already installed on your Mac to create an bootable USB for installing Windows. Since all Macs are the same, the Bootcamp Advisor sets up all the drivers correctly for you.</p>

<h3>Three weeks later</h3>

<p><blockquote><p>This is by far the most pleasant laptop I've ever used for development.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The screen is wonderful - the machine seems very fast and it is no weight to carry around.</p>

<h3>A tiny little gripe</h3>

<p>There is a little annoyance with the Bootcamp Control Panel which won't start properly, but Thomas Jespersen found a <a href="http://apple.stackexchange.com/a/59132/30710">workaround</a>, <a href="https://gist.github.com/3859956">which I've put in a batch file</a>. You need this to make the F1-12 keys work as they would in Windows.</p>

<h3>Some help with the Mac keyboard and trackpad</h3>

<p>I'm very picky about keyboards and I need to be able to find all my Visual Studio shortcuts in the same places. All in all I find the keyboard fine to work with.</p>

<p>The <code>delete</code> key works like a PC <code>backspace</code> so you have to do <code>fn+delete</code> to delete forwards. Here's a list of other shortcuts.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>PC (running Windows) </th>
<th> &nbsp;Macbook (running Windows) </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><em>Windows</em> key             </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>command</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>Del</em>                     </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+delete</em>  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>Ins</em>                     </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+return</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>Home</em>                    </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+left</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>End</em>                     </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+right</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>PgUp</em>                    </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+up</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>PgDn</em>                    </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+down</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>Ctrl+Home</em>               </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+control+left</em> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><em>Ctrl+End</em>                </td>
<td> &nbsp;<em>fn+control+right</em> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>&nbsp;
There are some keys which you will still not find, for instance, <code>NumLock</code>, <code>PrtScn</code>, <code>Break</code>.</p>

<p>If I need these, I use the On-Screen keyboard (type 'osk' into the search bar). If you cannot see the <code>NumLock</code>, the options allow you to show the numeric keypad. Alternatively, you could always plug in a USB keyboard.</p>

<p>The trackpad works great including the two-finger click for right-click and two-finger swipe for scroll.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
