<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: robots | ZeroSharp]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/blog/categories/robots/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-01T17:13:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Anderson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Robot Egyptologists]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/robot-egyptologists/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-01T11:52:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/robot-egyptologists</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is part of an ongoing series about robots, past and present.  See <a href="/skiing-on-mars/">Skiing on Mars</a>.</p>

<h3>Mysterious Shafts in the Great Pyramid of Giza</h3>

<p>Various robots have been used to explore secret tunnels in the Great Pyramid of Giza.</p>

<p><a href="http://http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Great_Pyramid_Diagram.svg"><img class="right" src="/images/blog/robot-egyptologists-001.png"></a></p>

<p>The tunnels were discovered in 1872 by Waynman Dixon, a British engineer who was helping with a project to undertake accurate measurements of the pyramid.  He noticed a crack in the southern wall of the Queen's Chamber and <strong>discovered a shaft hidden behind the masonry</strong>, as well as a similar shaft in the northern wall.  The shafts are very narrow (20x14cm) and so there was no feasible method of exploring them until recently.  The shafts in question are <strong>shown in red on the diagram above</strong>.  There are two similar shafts in the King's Chamber above it, but these have exits on the outside of the pyramid.</p>

<h3>Enter the Robots</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/blog/robot-egyptologists-003.jpg" title="Upuaut-2 (image credit Michael Studt)" >
<img class="left" src="/images/blog/robot-egyptologists-002.gif" title="The slab at the end of the southern shaft" >
In 1992-3, a series of robots were sent into the shafts to explore them.  The most advanced of these was <strong>Upuhaut-2</strong>, built by a German engineer Rudolf Gantenbrink.  It was able to <strong>crawl up the southern shaft 63 metres</strong> to reveal a stone slab blocking the shaft.  The slab has two copper clasps and looks like some sort of door.</p>

<p>In 2002, another robot, the <strong>Pyramid Rover</strong> designed by iRobot of Boston (the people behind the Roomba vacuum cleaning robot) in collaboration with the National Geographic Society took the exploration further by drilling a hole through the slab and inserting a miniature fibre-optic camera.  They discovered a space of a few inches followed by ... <strong>another door!</strong>.  The same robot was also able to explore the northern shaft which twists and turns more preventing earlier robots from getting very far.  It too ends up with a door approximately 63 metres from the entrance.</p>

<p>The <strong><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Djedi_Project">Djedi Project</a></strong> is a team of International and Egyptian experts currently dedicated to the further robot exploration of the tunnels via robots.  In 2011, it managed to drill a similar hole in the door at the end of the northern shaft.  The robot was also equipped with a miniature snake camera which was able to view the small chamber beyond the door and, in particular, <strong>some reddish hieroglyphs</strong>.  Here's a video from one of the sponsors of the project.</p>

<p><iframe width="640" height="390" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/CyUoF9977o0 " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>

<h3>References</h3>

<ul>
<li>Keith Payne's blog <a href="http://emhotep.net/2012/03/07/locations/lower-egypt/giza-plateau-lower-egypt/the-djedi-project-the-next-generation-in-robotic-archaeology/">Em Hotep</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.drhawass.com/events/mystery-hidden-doors-inside-great-pyramid-0">Dr. Zahi Hawass blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21028144.500-first-images-from-great-pyramids-chamber-of-secrets.html">New Scientist</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.cheops.org/startpage/thefuture/future.htm">Rudolf Gantenbrink's site</a></li>
<li>Images via Wikipedia, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mickythepixel/3903073791/">Michael Studt</a> via <a href="http://heritage-key.com/egypt/gizas-robot-explorers">Heritage Key</a>,</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Skiing on Mars]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/skiing-on-mars/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-27T11:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/skiing-on-mars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Mars_propm_rover.jpg"><img class="right" src="/images/blog/skiing-on-mars-003.jpg"></a>
This post is part of an ongoing series about robots, past and present.  See <a href="/friends-robots-countrymen/">Friends, Robots, Countrymen</a>.</p>

<h3>The Soviet PrOP-M Rovers</h3>

<p>In May 1971, the USSR launched two rovers to explore Mars.  <strong>They were to move on skis (!!)</strong> while connected to the landers with 15m umbilical cables.</p>

<p>The first one crash landed.  The second landed sucessfully but failed twenty seconds after landing and never moved.  The reasons are unknown although the landing took place in the middle of a dust storm.  The base module did manage to transmit about 20 seconds worth of the <strong>first ever photograph of the surface of Mars</strong>, shown on the left here.  According to the Soviet Academy of Sciences there is nothing, horizon or otherwise, identifiable in this photograph.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Mars_3_Image.png"><img class="left" src="/images/blog/skiing-on-mars-001.png"></a>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Soviet_Union-1972-Stamp-0.06._Mars_2.jpg"><img class="right" src="/images/blog/skiing-on-mars-002.jpg"></a></p>

<p>The rover itself, although never deployed, was equipped with sensors to detect obstacles (the two foremost metal bars in the photograph above).  <strong>The rovers were somewhat autonomous</strong> and capable of navigating obstacles.  The Soviet engineers were aware they might not have enough time for a remote-controlled operation of the rover (one-way communication takes between 4 and 20 minutes to Mars).</p>

<p>Receiving a signal from another planet, even for a few seconds is such an incredible achievement.  It's difficult to imagine what it was like being a programmer in those days, under that regime, but it must have been dramatic for those involved.  Hope, fear, pride, joy and perhaps disappointment and regret. <strong>All because of a chunk of metal sitting in a red dust storm <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=distance+between+mars+and+earth+on+December+2+1971">141 million kilometres</a> away.</strong></p>

<h3>Analog Computers</h3>

<p><a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/145669/what-software-programming-languages-were-used-by-the-soviet-unions-space-progra">Apparently</a> any programming would have been done on analog computers.  An analog computer does not require 'software' in the sense we use the term today.  Instead the computer evaluates an <em>analog</em>, a 'model' which corresponds to a given problem. You create the model by describing differential﻿ equations which correspond to the problem and then deriving a circuit corresponding to these equations. This is the 'program' of the analog computer. The computer itself has no memory and no algorithmic program control.</p>

<p>Watch a demonstration of how to program an analog computer to simulate a mass-spring system.  <strong>It's a far cry from my day job.</strong></p>

<p><iframe width="640" height="390" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/H_4bFgYReq0 " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>

<h3>References</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_2">Wikipedia Mars 2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_3">Wikipedia Mars 3</a></li>
<li><a href="http://cyberneticzoo.com/?p=3830">Cybernetic Zoo</a></li>
<li><a href="http://weburbanist.com/2011/12/04/star-cars-10-past-present-future-robot-space-rovers/">Star Cars: 10 Past, Present &amp; Future Robot Space Rovers</a></li>
<li><a href="http://web.mit.edu/slava/space/interview/interview-przhiyalkovsky.htm">Interview with Viktor Przhiyalkovsky</a></li>
<li>Images via Wikipedia</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Friends, Robots, Countrymen]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.zerosharp.com/friends-robots-countrymen/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-24T15:55:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.zerosharp.com/friends-robots-countrymen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first in a series of posts about robots, past and present.</p>

<p>Since at least the 1950s, people have claimed that we are just around the corner from a robot revolution.  Perhaps it's finally here!  The robots are coming!</p>

<p>Recently there have been substantial advances in many different overlapping domains: the driverless car, unmanned drones, machine vision, machine translation, machine learning, speech recognition, facial recognition, swarm robotics, self-reconfiguring modular robots, powered exoskeletons, nanotechnology, etc.</p>

<p>First up:  here's the <strong>rather terrifying</strong> DARPA AlphaDog Legged Squad Support System (LS3).</p>

<p><iframe width="640" height="390" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/xY42w1w0TWk " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.darpa.mil/NewsEvents/Releases/2012/02/07.aspx">DARPA website</a> says it can <strong>track a specific individual</strong>, so watch your back!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
